I think London is on a very very bad
path and something has [music] to be
done immediately. The police needs
rebuilding from scratch. I think
impartiality uh has gone um a little bit
downhill. We had one training in [music]
which um one of the questions asked of
us was as follows. how treating everyone
equally would [music] potentially lead
to inequality. You know, this is a
little bit Orwellian.
[laughter]
If something similar happens to 2011,
[music] I don't think we'll be able to
cope. We might be indeed [music] seeing
the total collapse of the police.
The British government wants to force
YouTube to downrank independent content
like ours and replace it with approved
messaging from the mainstream media. The
only way you can fight back and continue
to enjoy our content is to make sure
you're subscribed. Like this video and
comment below to have your say on what
the government is doing.
[snorts]
>> Dimmitar, welcome to Trigonometry.
>> Thank you. Thank you for having me. I
appreciate that. uh you're a former
police officer with the Metropolitan
Police.
>> Yes.
>> Uh we will talk about your story and
some of your views on policing and other
things that are happening. But the first
thing actually we wanted to talk about
is we both ourselves have experienced
this. You know I've seen people get
mugged repeatedly now in London and I I
don't spend a lot of time in London and
more broadly we hear from our
supporters, friends, people who live in
London that they just increasingly feel
less safe. Do you think there's a reason
for this? Do you think it's true that
people are less safe?
>> Uh yes, I think that's u most definitely
the case and I actually think u people
don't speak enough about how dangerous
London has become because they had
enough uh they have reached uh a level
of um detachment from reality only
because uh they have realized
they are speaking about a topic you know
they're bringing it up nothing really
happens. So a lot of people know how
dangerous London is, but they actually
don't talk about it. So your friends, I
think, are rather in a minority of
people who still talk about that topic.
Um, for example, the new statistics
saying that um the crime in London is
going uh downhill. Uh is going downhill
only because people are not literally
bothered to report it. And I'll give you
an example from my own self. I um I
don't have many many hobbies. One thing
I like a lot it's mountain biking. I'm a
big mountain bike fan. Uh so I bought me
a brand new quite expensive mountain
bike because I'm a big guy and I'm quite
heavy. So I wanted to buy a nice piece
of uh machinery there after a couple of
months got stolen.
I didn't report it myself. Why? Because
I know it's not going to go anywhere. So
yes, to answer your question, they're
absolutely right. Uh it's getting very
very volatile. Uh it's getting very
dangerous. I've seen that even when I
was um back in um back working for the
Met. I remember people will be you know
someone get their phone snatched and
then suddenly you know people getting
pushed away you know pushed on the floor
and then getting their phone snatched
then people branding knives and getting
your phone away. And I I was I was
seeing you know the the the violence was
escalating drastically. That's my
personal view to be honest. Uh also I've
seen that a lot of people started to uh
you know criminals um started to uh you
know attack police officers absolute uh
disrespect towards you know law
enforcement and and anything of uh such
sort. So uh yes uh I think London is on
a very very bad path and something has
to be done immediately.
>> And the question that will be on
everyone's lips is why is this
happening? And I think your personal
story ties very much into this. So why
do you think it's happening?
>> Okay. Uh from a police perspective I
think a lot of officers they call it
disillusionment with the job.
uh they understand in a way that they're
fighting a losing battle.
Uh I think for the first time in the
history of the Met uh voluntary
resignations has surpassed people who
retire.
>> Wow.
>> And that's that's absolutely
extraordinary. And whatever I say here,
everyone can go and look it up. uh I am
here mostly because I want to speak to
the regular member of the public you
know for the taxpayer and ask them to go
and check these things for themselves to
actually realize that the situation is
not it's not good at all so it's this
that disillusionment with the job it's
impossible tasks I used to work in uh
Westminster from being famous charing
cross police station it is not
exaggeration when I say that is non
stop call after call after call after
call. It is impossible for you to keep
on top of that, let alone proper
investigate further on. There are some
wonderful people still in the
Metropolitan Police and I think
Londoners are incredibly happy to have
them. I have been inspired by such
people. Probably that's why I last in
the med so long because I thought to
myself, not everything is lost. But I
think the the amount of work is
impossible. Nobody wants to join the
police because specifically lately
lately the the last few years you know
there was a lot of u bad media coverage
uh some egregious examples you know if
you want to speak about this egregious
examples later on you know we can we can
address that but uh they don't recruit
and they're losing mostly the best
people they have this is a recipe for a
disaster and it's just matter of time
before something happened and they won't
be able to control it and I think deep
down they know that. I really think deep
down, you know, the senior leadership of
the Metropolitan Police realizes that.
>> So tell us your story then. Uh how did
you decide to join the police? Why did
you join the police? And then what
happened from there and maybe just tell
you know a lot of people were saying
you've got an interesting accent. Just
tell us a little bit more about you.
>> Yes, of course. I am uh originally
Bulgarian and um I came to the United
Kingdom because um because of my
grandfather uh to put it that way from a
very very young age. Uh he taught me to
read the classics. So I started with uh
yeah with Russian classics um
unbelievable. You have to read those uh
you know probably and Gorki and uh you
know so much about life
>> if you want to be depressed. [laughter]
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. and informed and then I
moved to uh French classics. Yes, of
course. Wonderful. And then I ended up
with reading British classics and um I
thought to myself one day I want to go
to Great Britain, you know. And uh I
ended up in Liverpool. That was the
first place which I went to live. An
incredibly unique place. Uh not English,
not British Liverpoolian, you know, more
power to the people there. They are
very, very friendly. Some of the best
people I've ever met. However, deep down
I always wanted to come in London
because when I was in Liverpool, I'll
get the bus and I'll come to London. I
just going to walk around and I see this
magnificent city and I'm thinking about
the history that brought this city into
existence. All these lovely, amazing
people who made it happen for me to have
the opportunity to walk as a free man,
as an individual according to what I
think is the best values in the world,
the British values. That's what I think.
I sincerely believe that. And I was
thinking to myself, well, I am young. I
believe I have courtesy and dignity,
transparency and integrity. I'm
relatively fit. What can I do
to help this place, this country, this
city that I fell in love with preserve
itself and not only but make it the best
city in the world. And I think the best
position to do that is actually joining
the police because you can make an
everyday difference in someone else's
life and that person can remember that
and they can make that difference for
someone else and you can spread that
goodness upon hundreds of thousands of
people you know for the next 10 to 15 20
years. So I joined the police. I applied
I got the job. One day uh before I came
to London, I got you know a phone call
uh you know hello Dimitai you know you
on that university degree path uh
welcome to the uh police and you know
you're going to work becoming um the
best constable you can possibly be uh
while attain attaining to this um
university degree and uh you know even
further fulfill uh your professional uh
uh um you know goals and I'm thinking to
myself that sounds very nice in my head
I'm thinking This will be probably
something very well related to the
legislations
which a constable most definitely need
to know inside out. That's absolutely
paramount. So I thought to myself, okay,
you know, that's great. I'm happy. I
come to London. I find myself a place.
It was a little bit of a covid. We had
few lectures online and then eventually
we started going to university. And this
is the first time when I was starting to
think this is not very well conducted.
Brand new building in um in the city of
London, East India. Um I can name it. Uh
I was assigned to a university called
Anglia Ruskin University.
So we go there and uh sometimes in the
beginning I know it's the beginning
we're the first cause you know they used
to call us also the guinea pigs and
please bear that in mind because it will
become very relevant later on so we go
there in the beginning sometimes the
internet wasn't working very well you
know it's a brand new building that's
absolutely fine then uh guys you are in
room 10 oh no no no guys I'm very very
sorry you're in room 12 oh my apologies
you're in room 15 you know and And I'm
thinking to myself, um, this is all paid
with taxpayers money. Millions upon
millions of pound of pounds are
implemented into that program. And I
understand we are the first class. uh
but I think there must be some
expectations
from an establishment which is paid by
taxpayers money to be adequately
prepared to make the program you know uh
uh relative and you know uh smooth as
smooth as possible. Anyway, you know
those things they were a little bit um
strange but then u we started having
some lectures and uh um the materials
given to us uh I think a lot of it has
no relevance with the training of a
frontline police constable specifically
in the beginning of their career. For
example, um they used to teach us
theories such as broken window theory.
Well, that that that's okay. Maybe for
someone if if someone wants to expand in
the professional conduct in the future
to come as a criminologist, maybe they
can look upon that in the fullness of
time. But not at the moment. You need to
know how legislations
are presented
and uh how legislations are presented in
circumstances in which a constable may
happen to be part of you know was that a
burglary was that theft? Was that
robbery? Do you understand what to do?
You know we should be more police
oriented specifically about the job not
about theories. Then uh we had uh one
training in which um one of the
questions asked of us was as follows.
How treating everyone equally would
potentially lead to inequality.
You know this is a little bit Orwellian.
Yes. Yes. This is a little bit
Orwellian. I'm looking at that and I'm
thinking
officers, police officers in training
uh taught that question in a very very
interesting uh very interesting wording
you know and it seems to me it goes
against uh the very core principles of
uh impartiality you know it makes you
think oh my god what do you mean I'm
treating everyone equally and might lead
to inequality it's very very very
confusing very very confusing and I
think this is extraordinary bad thing to
introduce officers specifically some of
my uh colleagues who are very very young
people you know in their 20s and I'm
thinking they're getting confused here
and uh I thought to myself this is this
is crazy I don't want to be part of that
you know this is waste of taxpayers
money I want to be a police officer
people are getting robbed people getting
stopped selling drugs fights all over
the place let me be let me get off this
course and let me specialize you know
let me just be the officer I wanted to
be to protect this city and I truly mean
that from the heart. Anyway, so I was
very very lucky because my class my
class was actually very outspoken about
that on few occasions. We actually made
it very very clear the whole class that
we want to be taken of this course.
Guess what we were told on many many
many occasions.
Guys,
you either do this or you're going to
lose your job.
I want everyone that will be watching
this show just to think for a second if
they think it's appropriate to tell a
police officer in training that if you
do this, if you don't do this, I'm
sorry, you're going to lose your job.
That's coercion to the best, I think, to
the max. This is this is um really,
really, really, really bad. And when
they said that quite a few times, I was
looking around me and I could see the
faces of my colleagues. They were so
gloomy. You know, they had nothing to
say about that.
>> And just to interject one thing, I think
it's important to say that
>> one of the problems is that having a
university degree was made a requirement
for police officers.
>> Absolutely. And this is why you're all
sitting doing this course cuz I imagine
most of you would rather just be out
there being given practical skills to do
with how to police
>> in a heartbeat.
>> Right.
>> In a heartbeat. Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh and they used to say that quite a few
times. You know, guys, if you don't do
this, you're going to lose your job.
>> However, few days after that, they will
come and they will say, you know
something, don't worry guys, you're the
first class. You're going to pass. And
I'm sitting there I'm thinking this is
this is extraordinary thing to say. Um I
really was uh that was bewildering. Oh
don't worry guys you know um you know
you're the first class you know yeah we
have made some mistakes but you are the
guinea pigs like I've mentioned in the
beginning of our conversation. And I'm
thinking to myself this is this is
extraordinary conduct. You know if if
this uh is a serious uh university uh
you know uh I don't think they will be
acting like that. you know there will be
a dialogue there will be a discourse a
proper discourse of why we actually
don't want to be on that cause not be
told where we have to do it or you're
losing your job but um that was not that
was not the most extraordinary thing uh
we have been told on few occasions and
uh I'm not exaggerating and if uh some
of my colleagues are watching that I beg
of them to come forward and say the same
thing and I'm already I already spoken
to one of them and he said yes Dei I
clearly clearly remember that on one
occasion at least the lecturer who was
supposed to deliver a material to us
read that material to us said
she looked at the you know the
PowerPoint and she said and I quote oh
my god who wrote this please guys don't
shoot the messenger I'm only here to
read you that and I'm looking around me
I'm thinking am I drinking crazy pills
a lecturer openly mocking the very same
material they're going to deliver to us.
I went back to the station, you know,
after my university days and I said to
my supervisor and to my inspector that I
want to be taking off the course as soon
as possible and I stopped submitting any
work required, you know, of me uh and
everything I have have submitted before
that was um halfway uh through because I
I was really really scared that I'm
really going to lose my job. But
>> I reached a breaking point. I'm thinking
I cannot morally
continue like that. It may cost me my
job but I live my life on a very very
simple uh uh mode. So if it's not right,
don't do it. If it's not true, don't say
it. I couldn't. I really really
couldn't. So I stopped submitting um
anything. I haven't submitted anything
for probably 12 months. I haven't
submitted ditation, you know, final
work, nothing at all. uh and um I spoke
to uh chief inspector in learning and
development and they told me you need to
write us a letter and uh we're going to
assess the letter and if you meet the
exceptional circumstances crit criteria
you may be taking off the course. So I
write everything I told you in the
letter and I specifically said to them I
truly think it is indeed unexceptional
circumstances for someone to mock the
very same material they're going to read
as teachers that that's that's
extraordinary.
uh my application um wasn't uh
adequately uh under the umbrella of um
exceptional circumstances and uh I was
told that uh I have to continue with
that course. Then uh in a little bit
more strong worded email from my uh site
I said I am not doing this and that's
that you know and then after
[clears throat] I said that I sent that
email I received an email from another
external company which was given the
contract initially and that external
company has given the four universities
the ability to teach new offices. Uh and
uh that email sets me uh literally
Dimitar you either do this or you need
to resign and then it follows of course
I hope it's not data and you know we
want to help you out and that was a
breaking point that was a breaking point
because few days before that I did a
attachment with um ARVS which means uh
armed response vehicles and uh uh I was
so happy to be surrounded by such
professional police officers. And uh I
did uh 10 hours with them and in the end
of uh the shift they told me okay dear
uh you can send us an application and we
will see what we can do for you and I
know what that means you know I'll send
an application probably I'll be given a
chance to prove myself and eventually
join them if I pass all the assessments
required. So, I was very very happy. I
went back to, you know, to my inspector,
to my sergeant, and they was like,
"Deie, we're going to sign you off
immediately." Uh, you know, and you can
go specialize everywhere you want, but
we can't because you don't have the
degree. And this is when I sent the
email, and the email was comes back, you
either do this or you need to resign.
And that was a breaking point. I
resigned. I resigned uh two two days
after that. And uh my last day was on
the 31st of um uh March 2024. And uh it
was um a devastating moment for me and
for my partner. I'm not with my partner
anymore
because I became very very detached from
everyone, from her. Um I just couldn't
understand why this is happening.
>> The news doesn't just tell you what's
happening. It tells you what to make of
it. And the real red flag isn't what's
said, it's what gets left out. That's
why I use ground news. Every day, they
gather thousands of stories from across
the political spectrum, compare how
different outlets are covering the same
story side by side, and contextualize
it, including specific differences in
how each side is reporting it. That's
how you see what whole audiences are not
being told. My favorite feature is their
blind spot feed. Every day, it flags
upwards of 20 stories that are being
ignored by either the left or the right.
Let's look at some examples. Follow
along at ground.news/trigonometry.
Take this story. A Pew Research survey
found that 56% of Americans now support
banning social media for anyone under 16
with a majority of Republicans and a
majority of Democrats behind it. Genuine
bipartisan agreement is rare enough to
be newsworthy on its own. And yet,
coverage came almost entirely from the
right. The left barely touched on it. On
the other hand, look at this. An AP poll
found that 66% of Americans now say
democracy is central to what it means to
be American, down from 80% 5 years ago.
That is a serious story about how the
country sees itself, especially on its
250th anniversary. And it got three
times more coverage from the left than
it did from the right. Ground News puts
all of this in one place. headline
comparisons, bias breakdowns, ownership
insights, and context so you can
actually understand what's going on, not
just react to what you're told. Go to
ground.news/trigonometry
or click the link in the description of
this episode. Get 40% off their
advantage plan, the same one that we
use, and stop being managed by the
media.
I did had two exit interviews which is
quite um extraordinary on its own. on my
um second exit interviews. Uh on my on
my second exit interview, um the chief
inspector that wanted to help me out had
a conversation with the chief inspector
in learning and development. And uh they
were speaking for over 45 minutes, but I
very vividly remember she's saying to
her, I'm sorry, but um why are we losing
this officer again? He's public order uh
trained level two. He stays a train. He
speaks multiple languages. Um, his
inspector is here, his sergeant is here.
They're very very supportive of him. Uh,
his team is very very supportive of him.
Why are we losing him? I vividly
remember that. And I don't know what the
structure of the Met is what type of a
contract precisely they have signed with
this university awarding degree. I
really really don't know. But they
couldn't give me a decisive answer. They
wanted me to wait and I couldn't,
gentlemen. I couldn't. I was I was
broken. I love every moment policing
London and I think I have benefited
quite a few people to say the least. And
I think my colleagues can um uh quite a
few of them can say that I was a
substantive and well uh overall in
general compar uh uh complete officer to
begin with. I have done so many things
to help my colleagues. So many cell
exits with other teams which I don't
know anything about. Um pulled people
from the bridge you know going into the
battle if I may put it that way. I did
it so selflessly. I was really prepared
if the circumstances are such I'm not
exaggerating to lose my life if I have
to but to preserve human dignity and
goodness. And I sincerely believe that.
And probably that's why the impact was
so heavy on me and resulted in uh me
eventually breaking up with my
girlfriend. I was I was in a very very
dark place. I just couldn't um I just
couldn't take it anymore. At what point
I thought, you know, I I I lost my
meaning of life, you know. I was I was
good at it at this, you know. I just I
just wanted to to make a difference and
they have taken that away from me. And
uh I'm I'm not seeking vengeance. I just
hope people can hear my story so that
will never never happen again. To other
uh complete decent officers who wants to
make a difference because we need them
now more than ever. Uh to to to be
honest, more than ever.
Yeah. Yeah. That that that that uh it's
a little bit of a it's a little bit of a
sad story, but let me continue. I'm
sorry. I just had a little bit of a
flashback.
3 months after I resigned, it was a
beautiful summer day. I think it was
July,
you know, I'm at home doing nothing. I
open my laptop and I go to my private
email and I'm seeing there uh an email
from Anglia Ruskin. Congratulations,
Dimitar. We have awarded you a diplomat
policing. And um I'm thinking to myself,
um of course this is a mistake. They
have they have made so many mistakes.
you know, probably there was there's
some type of an explanation. You know,
that's not true. You know, maybe maybe
they they made a mistake like I said.
Anyway, I was free. Let me go into my
Anglia Ruskin profile. I go into my
Anglia Ruskin profile. Lo and behold, I
have been awarded a bartelo in policing
with no honors.
with no honor, which is an insult to
injury, you know, that that that is so
insulting to my intelligence that uh I
was so bewildered at that moment and
agree and angry. I'm thinking to myself,
I left because of this insanity and
eventually you worded that to me without
me submitting anything for over a year.
It was quite quite quite quite
interesting. I'm thinking to myself, let
me actually download that diploma
because that's that is extraordinary.
few months later because I still talk to
quite a few people um in the Met and in
the Met there's a lot of gossip but the
gossip in Met can be very very precise
because it's a very very close community
so the gossip most of the time is
actually quite accurate and I heard that
someone was awarded a degree not only
without submitting theation but without
submitting level two in maths
and I'm thinking uh it's possible man
it's possible If they're giving me a
degree without me submitting anything,
maybe they did that to someone else. Let
me double check. Let me just check. And
I send a freedom of information request
which I have is on my emails. Uh and the
freedom of information request goes as
follows. I think from memory. Has anyone
been awarded a degree in uh policing
without a submitting dissertation or b
submitting dissertation or level two
achieving level two in English or maths?
the freedom of information request comes
back and says none.
>> Yes. And I think I think
is either the freedom of information
request might not be truly uh accurate
or the university needs to explain how
this is actually possible to happen and
I wanted to find out. I went back to the
very building which we used to um you
know have our lectures uh in East India.
I go there they're not there anymore.
I'm thinking uh oh they're not here
anymore. Well they lost the contract
with with the Metropolitan Police. I
actually think by now uh the university
degree has been scrapped uh for I think
few years because the backlash was uh
nationally quite uh quite loud. you know
people say this is this is this is not
this is not working well people resign
because of it you know the amount of
work uh uh officers uh experiencing
policing London and on top of that they
need to do uh quite frankly in my
opinion um Alice in Wonderland the grits
quite uh quite striking and I go there
and said okay but do you know where they
have moved to uh where we don't know and
uh I I I can't find anyone from Anglia
Ruskin you know I wanted to go go there
with my diploma, tell them my
circumstances and just ask them how this
is possible. You know, tell me how how
was awarded that without me submitting
anything to begin with. It seems to me
the university never has taken into
account that there will be someone
like me that eventually will speak about
that. I think um they thought maybe to
some extent they can intimidate us but
that is not going to happen because
there bigger things about me and them
and the bigger things are the health and
wellbeing of Londoners and how the
police can preserve that. Not only
preserve that but to make sure the many
many problems of London which already
exist can be resolved. This is bigger
than me. This is bigger than them. We
need to find out exactly what's going on
because I think it's absolutely
outrageous.
>> And I think the worrying thing, look,
there's many worrying things about your
story, but the thing that resonates with
me is how are we meant to have good
police officers when we're not doing the
training programs that will prepare them
adequately for the job?
>> The frat, you have an answer for that
and uh I have to be very very honest.
I'm a big believer in uh individual
responsibility.
There were other officers like myself
that could say no, we are not doing
this. This is insanity.
However, for one reason or another, and
I understand I understand the price to
pay it's truly truly devastating. Like
in my case,
maybe some of them thought I'm just
going to get along with it and maybe in
future things will get better.
I don't think in future things will get
better. You are holding the office of
constable before you being a student or
anything else. It's absolutely necessary
for you to have that honesty
>> before anything else. I don't want to do
this. Don't only say it to to your to
the people in university or to your
sergeant. Speak to your colleagues.
Unite with your colleagues. Say it
clearly. I am not doing this. What are
you going to do? This is crazy. We don't
want to do universities degrees. I want
to be the best police officer I can. It
is up to them. They could stand up and
say, "No, we're not doing this." A lot
of them didn't for one reason or
another. I understand some people have
families. Some people need that income
but essentially to some extent they are
a little bit part of why this is
perpetuated upon them because they
haven't done enough. Maybe some of my
colleagues won't like that but I think
that's the case. You need to stand your
ground. It was crazy. It was insane. You
can't continue like that. You know the
struggle you have been through to get an
Alice in Wonderland degree again. I mean
why why you need to go through that
struggle taking so much away from your
time you know ears that will never come
back and I think it's up to them they
need to make a stand uh in in in in in
everyday policing as well um I am a big
believer that if you're frontline police
officer you should look after yourself
instead of finishing the shift and
saying oh you know guys let's go to the
p that's absolutely fine you socialize
but sometimes you need to say you know
guys let's go to the gym uh you can't
have um five or six officers jumping on
a on a on just a regular male who is a
little bit more volatile in order for
you to detain him. You know, you need
two, three officers maximum to be able
to do that. We already struggle with
numbers. We need to expand on standards.
But standards, no matter what you give
me, Francis, you can give me the best
training in the world. If I don't want
to do it myself, it will go nowhere. It
starts with an individual
>> but that also comes to recruitment
Dimitar because I mean look this is just
when I walk around London but I've
notice the standard of police officers
the way they conduct themselves the way
they dress
and and also the the shape that they're
in. I mean they don't look like they'd
be able to arrest anybody to be brutally
honest. And they don't necessarily look
very professional. Of course not all
police officers. There are a lot of
police officers that do, but even in the
40 or so years I've lived in this city,
I've seen a marketked decline in
standards.
>> I I agree with you. Yes. Um, you know,
I'm not a religious person. Uh, but
there are few things in the Bible which
are actually quite correct. You know,
open rebuke is better than secret love.
I wholeheartedly agree with you. Um
again I don't think um some of uh my
ex-colagues understand the incredibly
important nature
of the objective reality physical
reality of frontline policing. I'm here
to speak only about frontline policing.
You have to be most definitely in my
opinion above average when it comes to
uh an average fitness test. what an
average male can do or a female. Some of
uh one of the fittest police officer
I've ever worked with was a female. She
was always downstairs with uh with me in
the gym. She was incredible. But
I don't know what is stopping them. I
think I have a theory what is stopping
them. A very uh good friend of mine who
is still in the police. He's there I
mean a few decades now told me that a
lot of people come and when they see the
the horrible circumstances of what
policing means they become very very
cynical not only in their approach uh in
work but uh you know in their uh
personal lives and I think he's actually
correct it takes a lot of effort uh to
go to the gym. It takes a lot of effort
to be immaculate every single day. And
in my opinion, being a police officer
holding that uh incredibly important
role in London. It is a demanding
position. And if you're not ready to
reach that level, perhaps perhaps you
can go home, you can speak to someone in
work and say to them, you know, buddy, I
I don't think I'm I'm the best version
of myself. Uh uh let let me get let me
get some help. what can I do? You know,
uh I'm always giving people the benefit
of the doubt. I'll never say, you know,
that job is not for you. No, no, no,
never. I want to help you out, buddy.
But you need to do it on your own. And
like you said, yes. Um I quite often go
to uh uh central London and uh uh you
know I walk pass by people and um when
there's a police guy and suddenly few
officers looking like you just described
them come out I can just hear the public
oh my god look at them. Uh I mean it's
uh it's actually quite dangerous because
uh uh one gentleman uh was uh walking
and he saw these officers having a
coffee and he said they look like a
caricature in uniforms
and it's not only you. It's it's it's
it's
quite quite of a quite of a situation
and that situation can only be addressed
within the individuals to begin with.
However, the institution is quite
difficult to um uh to uh inspire them to
be that that that that best version of
themselves.
>> But surely Dimitar this comes from the
top. It's the people at the top who set
the standards of any organization.
Because if you don't set the standards
at the top, then look, there's some
people like yourself who are
self-motivated,
who really passionate, but there are
other people who are just there because
it's a job. And if you let standards
slip, then it's going to affect
everything and everyone. To me, this is
a crisis of leadership, isn't it? The
people who watch this show have
generally done more thinking about how
governments operate the most. But
there's a difference between
understanding the problem and having
actually built insulation against it.
That's the world MueL Thorp operates in.
He's been living as an expat for over 25
years, visiting more than 110 countries
and calling nine of them home. He
founded Expat Money nearly a decade ago
to help others do the same. When he
helps someone build an international
plan B, the knowledge he brings is
entirely firsthand. Every recommendation
comes from something he has already done
himself. Expat money works specifically
with freedom-minded families and
investors who want to reduce their
exposure on any one government or anyone
system. Second residencies, second
citizenships, offshore banking,
international real estate, legal
structures that spread your life across
borders. Muel has put together a free
report called Plan B residencies and
instant citizenships. It covers five
routes to a second passport, including
one that almost never gets discussed.
How a foreign residency functions as
genuine political insurance. Which
countries actually make sense depending
on what you're trying to protect and
what it realistically costs. Go to
expatmoney.com/trigger
or click the link in the description of
this episode to download the report.
There's no charge, no catch. That's
expatmoney.com/trigger.
To me, this is a crisis of leadership,
isn't it?
>> It is definitely a crisis of leadership.
And um let's speak about leadership
indeed. Um I think um I don't want to
offend anyone in the senior leadership
of the Metropolitan Police. Uh there's
some lovely lovely extraordinary great
people there. But in general, I think uh
they have reached a level of um
astonishingly
being capable of selfdeception.
And I call that the magic Excel
document.
We need 10 people to go to that place
and we need 20 people to go to uh you
know that protest you know let's see how
we can manage the numbers it's all about
numbers but the quality of officers it's
through the window it's all about
numbers and I always thought to myself
these people in these positions of so
much power and decision-m they should
know better than anyone else uh it's not
only about numbers
uh a football team has 11 players. If
you take Ronaldo and put me in, it still
be 11 players, but the performance will
deter it massively. I don't think to
myself, can they not see the bigger
picture? And unfortunately, I think
which is very very sinister. I think
maybe some of them do, but the next
promotion,
the next promotion is very well paid.
you have a lot of power if you are chief
inspector and above working for the
Metropolitan Police. It's a it it is um
it is a nice place to be. I think some
of them understand that. Uh and I would
like to say that quite a few of them
understand that quite well. But why
nothing is done? I think it's because
the politics are so um complex on that
level.
I think um
the police needs
rebuilding from scratch. Not today,
tomorrow before it's too late. It has to
be solely based on the pelium principles
and that's that. That's that nothing
else nothing more
>> which are what
>> uh well uh for example um you know treat
uh everyone equally I mean treat
everyone equally uh you know honesty uh
integrity uh um the the rule of law um
uh be uh impartial that's very very
important I think impartiality uh has
gone um a little bit downhill uh because
officers uh like this document I saw um
in um
uh this document I I told you I saw in
one of the trainings you know saying
that treating uh everyone equally can
lead to um unequal outcome
>> in inequal outcome yes impartiality is
uh very very very important very
important just uh work according to the
law bring courtesy back uh bring
discretion back I think officers have
been taking a a lot of discretion away
from them.
>> Uh and uh that that's a that's a big
problem. You know, I think uh you should
exercise more discretion of course based
on uh your impartial approach. Uh if
someone steals a sandwich because
someone has nothing to eat, of course uh
you're going to give them uh that
discretion uh and you're going to treat
them differently. If someone just steals
a sandwich because they can't be
bothered, you know, to pay. In that
sense, I understand. Yes. uh maybe your
treatment uh according to the particular
circumstances might be uh different but
uh discretion has gone you know
discretion is is over and I have been
through a situations like that which
discretion uh uh I thought to myself
could be implemented but it wasn't and I
don't know why
>> and uh this thing about uh equal
treatment leads to unequal outcomes uh
you're hinting at something that's been
a huge discussion in Britain which is
what people talk about as two-tier
policing.
>> Yes.
>> Uh and what they're talking about is a
mixture of things. It's not just about,
you know, racial disparities and things
like that, but it's, you know, the way
that protesters against lockdown were
treated versus BLM protesters and and
other things of that nature where the
public see that similar behavior results
in very different treatment. And then we
hear from people like you about
guidance. We hear from other people
about guidance around the treatment of
different racial groups. We see cases
like the Henry Novak case, for example,
where police officers arrive at a scene
immediately are effectively misled by
the races of the people involved as to
who's the perpetrator, who's the victim,
and overall a lot of people now have
this picture that the police have been
trained effectively at this point not to
treat people equally. Is this true? Is
this an exaggeration? What are your
thoughts on it?
>> Uh
when um in one of the lectures in
university um I think it was just a
little bit after uh uh BLM around that
time 2022 I think 2020 but I'm not very
very sure. I don't really remember uh
the very same lecture that said uh you
know guys don't shoot the messenger ask
a question from all of us um guys what
do you think about black lives matter
and a very lovely very good-hearted girl
in our class just said well uh all lives
matter and [laughter]
that I swear to God Constantine that's
exactly what you said
can you say that and I'm thinking can
you not see the goodness in this uh in
this uh you know uh young uh woman's
voice. Uh it was it was crazy. It it was
quite of a thing. Woo. Can you say that?
Uh and that woo can you say that makes
you think am I right to say that? That
all lives matter which is a perfectly
reasonable thing to say.
>> Am I right? Am I I maybe maybe I'm
wrong. Maybe I need to find within
myself where maybe I have some type of a
bias, maybe something that I don't
understand. It makes young officers
question themselves. You know, when a
perfectly reasonable statement like all
lives matter, it's absolutely fine. Of
course, black lives matter, all lives
matter, any lives matter. Um that woo
was was quite of a quite of a thing to
say. And um
>> were you ever asked about you know what
are your internal biases and things like
this?
>> Thank you. Uh I am going to say
something now. They were very very
clever with this. They gave us a white
piece of paper. Okay. And they say guys
this is anonymous. You don't have to
write your name. Just write down if you
think you ever had some privileges.
And uh I uh took that piece of paper and
I wrote I'm Bulgarian. My ancestors were
four and a half century under the
Ottoman Empire. Some of the savageries
have been well documented from
journalists from France to Russia and
the United States. I have more
privileges and I gave it to them. I
don't know what happened with that piece
of paper, but it was the most bizarre
thing that I've ever encountered in my
life.
>> What do you think was the point of that
exercise? Did you get a sense of what
they're trying to achieve by the
conversation about BLM, by the
conversation about privilege? What what
is it that they wanted you to learn?
I think this is this is my opinion. I
might be wrong, but I think giving
someone um this piece of paper and
asking that that question is solely
reading the room to what extent some of
the people here might think they might
have some privileges. And if someone has
put a privilege or something like that,
we need to address it. We need to train
them, you know. Uh
maybe we need to train people that
haven't put that they have any
privileges. You know, maybe they cannot
see it that you have a privilege and you
can't recognize it. You know, that's
what I think. I think it's way more
sinister than that. Uh without speaking
in depth of what exactly you mean
[snorts] someone has a privilege. I mean
uh this is a conversation that we can
have here for hours on end. It's uh
quite extraordinary to introduce that
out of the blue on a white piece of
paper and just give it to uh frontline
police officers who need to go back to
the street and you know tackle criminals
uh you know and wrestle with them on the
floor. What privileges are you talking
about? Jesus Christ.
>> Yeah.
>> It's it's so extraordinary. I I I guess
what I'm getting at trying to
understand, not getting at, I'm trying
to understand is what the truth is about
the idea that police officers have been
trained now for some years to treat
different people differently. Is this
something that you see or saw on whether
on the front line or in your training or
anything? And I'm open to the
possibility that maybe it's exaggerated
or maybe it's not true, but I'm I'm
really trying to understand what your
perspective is on it. Uh well this
document was um obviously introduced to
some police forces. Um the question
which was introduced to us that's
definitely was uh uh in regards to the
metropolitan police. I think um when you
introduce
fundamentally
such incredibly difficult topics without
very much explaining them. you're
putting a seed of
questioning
uh the person start questioning
themselves do everything I know and do
actually might be biased it's confusing
them if you suspect let's say for the
sake of argument that someone may be
biased or have some um inclination
towards treating different people
differently maybe people that look like
him Just for the sake of argument, you
may have a training uh I mean the
training is already there. The the the
police fundamentals I I I like I said
they're already there. Transparency,
honesty, in honesty, you know,
impartiality. You don't need to make
these young people questioning
themselves all the time because
eventually they will be confused and
eventually when you're confused
sometimes in a situation which requires
your immediate professional attention as
in the case of may he rest in peace this
young man Henry Novak may lead to um
tragic outcomes
and um that thing with I don't think so
mate
makes my blood boil. To begin with,
nobody should ever speak to a member of
the public regardless of the
circumstances. Even if you're a suspect,
even if I know you're the bad guy, hey
mate, don't approach people like that.
Eventually, maybe you get to know
someone and speaking to them for 5 10
minutes. Maybe then you can, you know,
slide it in. Hey, thank you, mate. Thank
you very much. But in the beginning, as
I said, you represent the office of a
constable. You need to be immaculate in
my opinion of speaking to these people.
I always approach even the suspects.
Even the suspects, you know, hey,
tomorrow is a better day. I'm not here
only because of them, of the person that
call me. I'm here because of you as
well. Let me see how can I help you out.
I never approach anyone. Hey mate,
listen to me mate. That's extraordinary.
I've seen that. It only escalate things.
And um in the case of Henry Novak,
why they haven't
give why they didn't attend to him
medically, it's it's uh it's seriously
beyond me. Uh fundamentally, the most
important thing of policing is preserve
life.
Even if I know this guy's a vict, you
know, this guy, he he is the
perpetrator, you know, I just I just saw
him shooting that fell over there, but
that fell is being attended already. And
in the process of me detaining him, I
knock him out so badly that he doesn't
want to come back to, you know, to to to
life, you need to immediately attend to
him no matter what he have done. If if
there's so if there's deranged man on
the street stabbing people and in the
process of you detaining him you shot
him in the leg or you shot him in the
chest, you know, immediately you need to
attend to them as well. You need to
preserve their life by all means
necessary. They should have stripped him
and I'm sorry to say naked immediately
and see if he's bleeding, not just roll
him over and put in a handcuffs. This is
uh you know I can't watch this video. I
watch it a few times and I can't anymore
because it makes me uh truly truly truly
truly sad. Truly sad for this 18year-old
young man. It's it's just the most
egregious thing I've ever seen in my
life. When you buy seafood, what do you
worry about most? Nutrition,
sustainability, taste. I've asked all of
those questions. This is why Wild
Alaskan Company caught my attention. It
is the best way to get wild core,
perfectly portioned, nutrient-dense
seafood delivered to your door. You've
not tasted fish this good. When we first
got a delivery from Wild Alaskan
Company, it stood out immediately. The
care that goes into it, the packaging,
the clear sourcing, their attention to
detail. You can tell this is a company
that does things properly. What makes
Wild Alaskan Company special is how they
source everything. 100% wild core, never
farmed. No antibiotics, no GMOs, no
additives, just clean real fish frozen
off the boat to lock in flavor and
nutrients like omega-3s. You get
flexible shipments, expert cooking tips,
and a box that genuinely feels like it's
come from people who care about what
they're sending. My favorite variety is
their Pacific Halibur. Firm and meaty,
it cooks beautifully in a pan or on the
grill and goes with almost anything. And
there's no risk if you're not completely
satisfied with your first box. Wild
Alaskan company gives you a full refund,
no questions asked. Get seafood you can
trust. Go to wildalaskan.com/trigg
for $35 off your first box of premium
wildcourt seafood. That's
wildlaskan.com/trigg
for $35 off your first order. Thanks to
Wild Alaskan company for sponsoring this
episode.
>> And I think a large part of the problem,
Dimitar, is
>> if you you wanted to be a firearms
officer.
>> Yes, indeed. And I think a lot of people
don't want to be firearms officers
anymore because they go, "Well, if I do
my duty and I shoot someone who is
posing either a threat to me or a threat
to the public or both, I'm the one who's
going to get arrested here."
>> Uh, yes, Francis. Absolutely.
I don't think like that. I don't care.
And I don't care in a way of I
understand that things bigger than me. I
truly believe that justice for all it's
bigger than the preservation of my own
life even sometimes maybe my own
freedom. I wanted to join arm response
knowing this might be the case but I am
prepared to face the consequences and I
was ready to face the consequences
because I knew deep down inside of me I
will be so well prepared so well
prepared. I will train myself every
single day not only in my physical
ability to do something.
my tactics, my firearm tactics, my
communications, even if it's only in my
head, my knowledge of the legislations.
So if that time comes one day, I will
face it as a man who believes has
reached that level of professionalism.
And whatever may happen after that, I
don't care because they're bigger things
than me. I can't just say to myself, oh,
you know something, I don't want to do
this. you know, I just want to have a
family and you know, maybe someone else
can do it. No, no, no, no, no, Francis,
it's necessary. Someone has to do it and
I was prepared to do it. But I
understand that, Dimitar. But there are
people who are going, "Look, if I do my
duty and I'm going to get punished for
it, then what then? Why would I do that
job?"
>> Well, look at the Chris Kabak case.
>> Look at look at the I mean, you you're
the guy who wanted to be a firearms
officer. I'm not Francis isn't, but this
is a situation where someone has
committed firearms offenses.
>> Mhm.
>> Is using his car to try and ram police
officers. An armed police officer shoots
him. And there's a big there's a big
media hoopla about this. And the guy's
the guy the officer who shoots him is
tried for murder.
>> Yes, he is tried for murder. Um I think
uh
>> this is it's it's grotesque.
>> It is grotesque. Um
this country it's um was famous once
maybe one day again for probably having
the best justice system in the world.
>> Uh very rigorous, very open, you know.
Uh we all put in the same uh uh you know
level and uh we all be uh you know
judged accordingly. So open scrutiny is
very very welcomed you know very very
welcome though the portrayal of what
happened there
>> in my opinion was indeed um actually
taken away from uh an impartial honest
process but it was a little bit one way
uh this officer is a murderer
seriously
what do you know about uh air training
what do you know about receiving an
information about a vehicle which was
linked to armed offenses. Someone tried
to ram you with their own car, maybe
having a gun because that's information
you have. Maybe they're trying to ram
with you you with with the car, but
maybe next to him there was a gun. You
don't know that. You know that that
vehicle is linked with guns. And not
only that, he's trying to ram me with
his car. What do you think is the best
solution in that split second? the
police officer in question has made that
decision
and I think the decision was based on
self-defense and defense of others
because I was walking in North London
and uh this chap came up to me and he
said I love trigonometry. I want I want
to let you know that I'm a police
officer. There's a lot of police
officers that watch the show and one of
the things a lot of the people in the
force believe is that neither senior
leadership nor the politicians have our
backs.
>> Uh there's a incentive like that. Yeah.
Quite quite strong within the
Metropolitan Police. Yes.
>> But it's true, isn't it? Like I mean of
they clearly don't have their backs
because if they did in this situation
the guy would get a medal, not a murder
trial,
>> right? uh uh they could be uh they could
they can receive an award for exemplary
work. Yes, that that can that can be the
case most definitely. Or they were uh
acquitted I think quite quite fast. So
there's some hope still though um
>> he should never have gone to trial
never.
>> Maybe for I think I'm not defending them
by all means necessary uh the people who
took him to trial. Maybe for the sake of
uh that seeking that ultimate justice um
it was um you know this officer was put
through indeed a horrific I think you
know uh uh trial you know and uh uh
that's I can only imagine what he has
been through but uh it was not that much
about the trial it seemed to me to be a
witchcraft like they were trying to
convince him I think that's the problem
it's not uh questioning uh Oh, let's see
exactly what happened. What you have
done? Could you have done anything
better? All these questions that they're
asking you. I think it was a a witch
hunt day. Witch hunt. Yes. That's what I
think. That was the problem. Yes.
>> And but this is this is kind of what I'm
getting at is um you say, you know, in
the interest of absolute justice, but
but as you know better than I, justice
there this justice is a nuance thing.
There are different people. If you hound
a police, an armed police officer in the
way that he was hounded both in the
media, by politicians, by activists, and
you put him on trial for murder when
he's clearly not only done the right
thing, but done the courageous thing in
very difficult circumstances, that's not
justice, that's injustice. And this is
something that a lot of people feel has
now happened in the country where the
rights, I'm using inverted commas for
people listening, of perpetrators of
crime, which is what Chris Cabba was. he
was a criminal.
>> Yes.
>> Are placed far and above the interests
of the ordinary person who is the victim
of those crimes or in this case of the
police officer whose job it is to stop
criminals like Chris Ka doing what they
do.
I think to some extent there might be
some
ideologues within um uh the system um
the police, the the the courts uh which
indeed may um perpetuate some ideologies
um and uh therefore
affect the process of justice. Uh now
why we have um people like that in such
position of power, positions of power is
um beyond me. I don't know how they
selected. Uh I don't know uh how they
think. I don't know if they can't see
for themselves that uh this is actually
not transparent. I say that word quite
quite often. This actually is leaning
one way rather the other. Uh let's not
forget that uh the courts are there for
uh one thing and one thing only to be
absolutely honest and clear about the
picture. Their job is not to try to find
someone guilty or not guilty but to find
out what is the truth. And you here come
very very correct. Unfortunately, I
think we're living in a situation in a
world in which truth
can be interpreted very differently
according to the people, you know,
people in power. And that worries me a
lot because
um if we're going to have an ideologues
making decisions
what is wrong and what is right then we
on a very very slippery slope of u and I
think we're very very close to a point
of no return with some insanities going
on in London and in England to begin
with
>> because we're talking about ideologic.
>> Yes. I mean there's there's a lot of
problems with that but one of the major
problems is ideologues see the world
through their lens. It's an ideology and
with policing you can't have ideology.
You have to have reality.
>> Absolutely. Yes. Yes. Correct.
>> So you look at something like stop and
search and people were going oh we need
to get rid of stop and search. Now again
I've never policed a day in my life but
to me that seems lunacy is particularly
>> it is lunacy. It is absolutely crazy.
>> Why why is it lun?
>> Uh I would tell you uh stop and search
is very very controversial. Um because
according to um statistics um uh black
kids um maybe stopped a little bit more
uh than uh you know anyone else. Okay.
I've done few stop and searches and I um
will tell you something specifically
when I was in um S&T safer neighborhoods
team. Uh most of the stop and search
were uh searches were in relation to
drugs you know if you can find some
drugs on them you know drug
paraphernalia. Uh because these kids
they go into uh inside properties you
know on the staircase and they smoke
weed and they listen to loud music. Well
guess who is calling us there. It's the
black lady next door who had enough of
them. Guess who called us again? The
black gentleman who told me, "I can't
this deal with these kids anymore. Not
only they're getting, you know, uh uh uh
high on my in front of my apartment on
the staircase." Last time one of them
pissed in an elevator. The people who
are calling me to do the stop and search
and go and attent
themselves. There were black lovely
people living in these buildings who had
enough of kids running up and down
smoking weed and causing havoc, you
know, steing your bikes and like uh this
guy said, you know, pissing in the
elevator. So, um stop and search is not
exactly as people think. Most of the
time uh it's uh other black folks
calling on you know these kids. some of
the stop and searches in um Soo for
example. Uh Sooho is very famous for um
getting your phone snatched um your uh
watch uh snatched.
If um there's a hot crime spot
and um you are dressed
in um you know uh black uh Nike uh you
know tracksuit with a mask on. Of course
that's not enough for anyone to stop and
search. maybe just the way you want to
dress, you know. But um when um you're
running away from the police and you try
to hide yourself away from the police
and before that there was an intelligent
sources described someone like you
feeding that description of just robbed
the phone 20 minutes ago. You might be
indeed get stop and search. Not because
you might be guilty, but you may fit
very very well the description of that
person found in that exact location in
which 20 minutes ago someone got their
phone snatched, you know, and you really
really look like that that that person.
If you uh have uh um nothing to hide,
that's absolutely fine. You can stop and
search me, you know. If you if you got a
description of Eastern European guy, you
know, looking at me, snatching phones,
you know, I want to be stop and search
as soon as possible because I want to
eliminate myself. I want the bad guy
actually to be found. So stop and search
most of the time in my opinion, looking
at my colleagues as well, it's very very
well researched. It's not done for the
sake of stopping and searching people.
That is not true. That is not true.
Actually, the stop and searches which
have been conducted are very very
professional. You know, very curtious.
They take their time. They explain
everything in detail. They're willing to
give you a record of the stop and search
if you think it was not right for you to
go and you know and say, you know, I
don't think that was right. You know, I
don't think that officer stopped me for
the right reason. And that never happens
because most of the time the
intelligence sources are quite um uh
quite spot on.
>> And it's not just crimes, it's also
preventing crimes. Yes. But if you've
got the report that that somebody's
carrying a knife,
>> you could be saving someone's life.
>> Absolutely. Yes. Yeah. And knives are
knives are
um how can I put it? Much more um
prelevant that people think. A lot of
people carry knives. Uh however, they
tend to hide them sometimes near them.
If they're in a particular area, they
might not carry the knife with them all
the time. But uh if another gang comes
uh they know where the knife is and uh
they can run and get it. So uh a lot of
people might be found not carrying a
knife but they might have knives
somewhere close to them or within some
of their friends which haven't been uh
stopped and searched. Knives it's it's
an epidemic. It's it's a really epidemic
and it's extremely dangerous. Yes, I
agree with you. Uh and they have ways
around it, you know. Uh uh they they
know what to do. They really really do.
People who actually carry knives,
they're quite well educated on the
topic, if that makes sense. They really
do know what
>> what does that mean, Dimitar?
>> Well, like I said, they might hide the
knife, they might hide the drugs. Uh
they might not have it on them. So, um
let's say um 20 minutes ago, you saw
someone matching my description, you
know, pulling, you know, having a knife,
you know, just putting a knife in my in
my in my pocket. Okay. And um however in
this 20 minutes that until the police
come and found me you know I'm in my
area you know and I'm let's say I'm I'm
doing something dodgy there you know but
I know you know I don't want to carry
the knife with me you know I'm going to
be here let's say for the next half an
hour I may leave the knife somewhere
close by and on my way out of this area
I can just pick it up with me. So you
have that information, you come, you
stop and search me, but the knife is not
on me because I've stashed it somewhere.
That's it.
>> And now you've committed a point uh
whatever the term would be, a pointless
or a fruitless or a baseless stop and
search and you are now
>> respective. It's negative. Yeah, it's
negative. Yeah.
>> And why is there an epidemic of knife
crime in London?
>> Because of how volatile the city is. the
cities. Uh I will give you an example
which I think fits the characteristics
of London quite well. I'm from Eastern
Europe.
I said that to all my friends, Eastern
European friends across the seas. My
English friends, pick any Eastern
European country. Pick any city in any
Eastern European country, any street,
any day, any time. I will walk there on
my own. No worries. I would never ever
do the same in London in some areas.
Never. I'm going to get jumped. I I
won't. I won't. I I am I am genuinely
scared. I'll do that everywhere else in
Eastern Europe. Lovely. With with
pleasure here. I won't do the same
thing. I go back home sometimes and I uh
say to, you know, people in in Bulgaria,
probably European country, how dangerous
London is, and [snorts] they look at me
in disbelief, in in in absolute
disbelief. I said, "Well, yeah. Oh,
yeah. Fights, um, your watch gone,
people getting stabbed almost on daily
basis." Uh I think I'm not very very
sure 40% of all mobile snatches in
continental Europe I think are conducted
in London. I'm not very very very sure
but it's something extraordinary like
that.
>> Dean, can you check it out with Venice
AI? It's it's what we use to fact check
things while we're conver
I'm interested to see.
>> Is it true that 40% of phone snatching
in Europe is in London? Just check that.
>> Thank you. Um,
and do you put that down to the problems
of policing that you told us about,
which is effectively if you don't have
enough police, if you're losing good
police officers, if the quality of the
police officers declining, we know, you
know, under Theresa May's government,
there were slashes to uh or when she was
home secretary rather, there was huge
budget slashes and therefore you
couldn't you lost tens I think over
10,000 police officers. is the reason
London has become less safe and more
there's more crime because there's not
enough good police officers.
>> I think it's partially because of that.
>> And what else?
>> Apathy. People don't care. People think
that they can get away with everything.
The social cohesion of so-called
diversity is our strength in London in
my opinion is a fairy tale.
I have never seen a city so beautiful
with so much potential and yet so
divided. I I am I am really really
shocked to see that. I think a lot of
these young kids, these gangs, they
don't care. They have absolutely no
connection to anyone and anything but
the gangster lifestyle. uh because it
seems so easy to get away with it and
yes it seems so easy to get away with it
because um like you said you know
there's not enough police officers. The
second part is even there are some
police officers like Francis said they
look at them I'm think and they're
thinking probably they look like um you
know a sack of potatoes in uniform. I
outro dam officer they try to deter push
them over and get away with it. I think
all those factors contribute to that.
>> You know, it's interesting you say that
you guys were talking about this. I saw
I was scrolling my Twitter that
yesterday. I saw this video of uh a guy
promote posted this video saying, "Oh,
the police in in London don't about
and and it's u it's guys on bikes
snatching phones and then a police
officer comes in and just smashes them
off the bike or they tackle them off the
bike or they ram them. not ram them with
a car, but they sort of enclosed them.
>> And I was like, "Oh, wow. This is Oh,
have they changed policy?"
>> That's an AI.
>> I watched as well yesterday.
>> I was like, "Oh, this is what we want."
Oh. Oh, okay. It's AI.
>> That That was an AI. Yes. Yes, it is. It
is.
>> Sort of tells the full story, doesn't
it?
>> It is. It is. It is indeed exactly that.
It's apathy. They They don't care. Um
police are not there to begin with. They
don't look respectful enough to a police
officer should be especially frontline
police officer should be to some extent
possessing authority. So when I see to
police officers coming from a police car
I want to think for myself. You know
something man I rather I rather do you
know what I got to do.
>> I don't want to mess with I don't want
to mess with this guy.
>> Exactly. I don't want to get you know
detained by these officers. You know
he's not going to be and they obviously
seems like they're going to detain me.
you know, or maybe I should do something
else with my life. Uh, however, these
officers are getting less and less and
far between
>> and that's uh a tragedy and the
taxpayers are paying for that.
>> Dean, did you were you able to look it
up?
>> So, the UK as a whole accounts for about
40%.
>> Okay. So, the UK as a whole is 40% of
all phone snatching in Europe.
>> That's uh I mean
>> that's insane.
>> That that's that that's that's crazy.
Oh, uh Constantine. Um, it's it's it is
beyond belief how bad it is.
>> Can I ask a question? Cuz cuz this
really like this is going to this as a
Londoner, this boils my urine.
>> You see these kids, you see them nicking
phones.
>> Yes.
>> You see them cycling around. I don't see
a police officer. I'm like, why don't
you arrest this kid? I mean, it's not
exactly a difficult crime to solve.
>> They don't have enough people, Francis.
Like I said, spec specifically um
Westminster, which I used to work, you
go from coal to coal to co to coal and
to some extent if you're experienced
police officer and you are let's say on
Oxford Street and very very quickly you
need to go to I don't know um just
region street it's not that far away
you know somebody snatched your phone
let's be very very precise I snatched
your phone until the victim finds
someone to call the police.
Until the police ask you a few
questions,
>> until a police unit is dispatched to
come and see you, the fellow on the
bike, it's in Lambbeath
in that electric bike. You know, he's in
Lambert. He's And a lot of police
officers, they know that. Yes, of
course, they're going to put the blue
lights on and they're going to try to
come and speak to the victim as soon as
possible. That's absolutely fine. But
deep down they know the whole process
until they get dispatched until they
come and see you. Especially now Oxford
Street will be uh you know made for
pedestrians alone is that's going to be
a crime heaven. That is going to be
something else. Your phone is gone. So
they know that. They know that. But I
will say something a little bit
controversial.
Snatching phones. It just a little part
of actually what is going on in London.
The robberies are something else. Uh
people being threatened with knives, uh
beaten in front of their wives and
partners, you know. Um there few videos
like that on on social media getting
their, you know, watches away from them.
The the violence is escalating quite a
lot. A lot of people are not afraid to
stand in front of police officer and
abuse them. uh sometimes even become
physical with police officers and I
think um I think that's very very very
telling very very very telling I have uh
a colleague who in one of these protests
which used to happen every Saturday got
dragged in in the crowds I think they
stole her helmet I think they stole her
but button and I think they broke her
hip I'm not very very sure if she had a
broken hip or not and then they they
spat her
Yeah, I mean uh uh it's u it's it's it's
really really bad. It's really really
bad. If something similar happens to
>> in London, I don't think uh we'll be
able to cope.
>> You're talking about the riots.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Tim, it's been an absolute pleasure
having you on.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh we're going to go to questions from
our supporters. I really thank you for
coming on. And I think it's really
important for people like you to come
forward to tell your story
>> and to explain to people
>> at the normal level of the person, the
frontline police officer and this will
be true in the NHS, it'll be true in
prison of service in many different
areas what's actually going on because
politicians talk about politics and
media people talk about this at a
political and media level. But just to
hear your story from your experiences
has been really valuable. So thank you
for coming on. Before we get to
questions from our supporters, what's
the one thing we're not talking about
that we really should be?
>> Before Dimitar answers the final
question at the end of the interview,
make sure to head over to
triggerpod.co.uk
where you'll be able to see this. What
does the public most misunderstand about
being a police officer?
>> Why is there two-tier policing?
>> Is it now time for all police officers
to be armed with guns?
What's the one thing we're not talking
about that we really should be?
>> The very painful topic of um
introducing
higher standards when it comes to
recruitment.
The very topic of um
few
[snorts] I have to say it. I think to
some extent the front line has been um
quite saturated by um
female [snorts] officers which are
absolutely wonderful in what they do.
But when it comes to volatility and
being able to objectively restrain
someone,
I think they are not prepared to such
level of violence and they need a lot of
backup sometimes. And because they need
backup, most of the times they're taking
away a unit that might be dealing with
someone else. If we had more officers
that's absolutely fine. I want and I
wish everyone the best. I want everyone
to expand in their work. But we are at
such stage of uh um low numbers that if
we don't address the quality of
policing,
we might be indeed
uh in the next few years uh seeing the
total collapse of the police. in my
opinion.
>> And uh what do you think the answer to
that is? Because when we had Chris Chris
Donaldson who's a former police officer
himself and in fact he worked his way up
I think uh he he mentioned that you know
we talked about the the fe the female
aspect of this that you bring up the
physical strength of being able to deal
with violence and what he said is the
the thing is there's a flip side to this
which is female officers can quite often
diffuse a situation in a way that men
are less likely to do which I think is I
suspect is probably partly true. So is
it about having the right mix or
partnering people in the right way or
having more people or do do you think
it's it's just a question of people
being put into positions for which
they're not suitable?
>> Uh I think um
uh DEI
uh has introduced um few of these uh
policies that uh you know we need a
certain amount of that type of people
certain amount of these type of people
which is absolutely crazy. That's insane
because the moment you say I need more
uh Bulgarians, you know, give myself
into example, you are taking away the
opportunity of someone else that might
be much better suited for that position.
And that that that's that's true. Um and
I disagree actually with that that
they're better in diffusing uh
situations.
Diffusing diffusing a situation needs
courtesy and professionalism. That's the
only thing that it needs. It doesn't
matter where it comes from. As long as
the other person can see that is genuine
regardless if comes from me or you or um
some other uh lady, it truly truly
doesn't matter. It has to be sincere.
Courtesy is something that you cannot
fake. Discretion is something that you
cannot fake.
Maybe uh some uh female officers may
possess that more naturally. But then
again, what makes a a person naturally
more cocousious? Uh that that we can't
uh we can't pick and choose um when it
comes to the reality of frontline
policing. I rather have someone who is
more physically capable of doing things
and then work on their courtesy uh and
discretion than someone that has only
courtesy and discretion. But uh it's not
working on the physical ability to do
something because uh uh most criminals
uh really don't much care how cous you
are. Uh especially if they're guilty,
they want to get away. They want to get
away. Of course, that doesn't mean you
have to approach them. Hey mate, but um
they really really don't care. They are
thinking I'm how I'm going to get out of
this, what I'm going to do, what I'm
going to say. You know, it's it's whole
uh avalanche in their head. Uh so to
some extent they might be right, but I
wouldn't myself use that as a theory to
just put more curtious people regardless
of their sex.
>> Well, and we saw it I mean with the
Manchester ter the Manchester airport
>> Yes. confrontation. I mean,
you feel sorry for the for the female
police officers involved in that
situation who were badly injured, but
but you you you you in in as you just
said earlier, in an ideal situation,
those guys who punched police officers
really should have been very hesitant to
do so because of the stature and the
presence of those police officers and
they would ideally be thinking, I don't
want to punch these people because
that's going to end very badly for me.
>> Yes, absolutely. And and clearly that
deterrent wasn't there which is what
you're saying.
>> No, it wasn't. It wasn't. And um it's to
some extent I actually think it might be
invitation
>> of course.
>> And um uh I think uh we should address
something else here as well. Um which
again may sound controversial but um
uh we live in a
very very multicultural society.
>> Mhm. And uh I think uh perhaps we have
to take into consideration that some
cultural upbringing
may have different views
on women. [laughter]
>> Yeah, I think we might. Yes, that that
is very very very important. And um
>> Oh, I see even more what you're saying.
I So when it comes to policing, the way
somebody from a certain background might
react to a female police officer is
different. Yes, absolutely. I've seen
that many many times. I've seen that
many many times. I've been uh I have
done very many sale exits. Sell exit is
um when someone is very very angry and
uh you know you need to detain them
inside the uh the cell and you know
there's a particular way how you get
away from them and um
I have seen people being angry being
handled by uh female police officers uh
quite often. um and they come from uh
most of the time
particular backgrounds in uh North
Africa and Southeast Asia most of the
time. And um I have experienced that
myself. I have experienced people
telling me, "Oh, why with English?
You're like us. You're a foreigner.
You're one of us quite a few times."
Most of the times they think I'm Russian
because of my family name.
>> Yes. Uh and uh
they have been told me why we them you
know why why we English they never say
the British.
>> Yeah
>> they say the English we think uh we are
British. Uh they they think this is
England. It's it's quite interesting
that we want to uh achieve um uh
something which is uh you know under the
United Kingdom. We're all British but
they don't see uh the the locals as
British. They see them as English. to
some extent I think the animosity is
quite open
>> and I'm very very very so sorry to say
that but I have experienced that myself
I have seen it I have heard it many many
times oh why you helping them you know
why join the police are crazy stuff like
that you know from uh quite a few quite
a few people
>> and it's also as well let's be honest
about that in this country you're taught
never to hit a woman now some people do
because they're not very nice people
they're not good people morally but that
is what were taught in this country.
There are other cultures they don't
really have an issue with it. Francis um
the insanity
of the s this this is my opinion again
you know I think it's an insanity uh
what we have found ourselves to be in
let me paint the picture people in suits
paid by taxpayers money going to the
home office okay for months
thinking about what we are going to do
and came out with leaflets saying you
need the other person to say yes before
you have sex. Don't have sex with
someone who is asleep. For the love of
God, are we living in a age of total
delusion?
>> Yes.
>> This is this is crazy. You know, I I
said that to my sister and she thinks I
am I am joking. You know
>> people outside of Britain think uh uh uh
you people are totally nuts and and I
mean that because I feel sorry for this
country that has given so much to the
world and it doesn't really matter in my
in my case where I have come from
because where you come from yes indeed
matters a lot but essentially what
matters is your ideas what you believe
in how you want to live your life that's
why I have chosen to live in Britain I
don't consider myself British maybe one
day if I marry a British lady and we
have kid maybe that kid will be British
but not me. I consider myself as a
subject of this great place and I want
to help out but I am afraid to say that
I think I'm in the minority. There's a
lot of people who don't think that way
whatsoever are openly hostile and for
the United Kingdom governments who
approve that I think uh tells you
everything you need to know of where we
are heading.
>> Absolutely. Dimitar it's been an
absolute pleasure. Thank you so much for
coming on the show. Make sure to head
over to our subst where you get to ask
Dimitar your questions.
>> He says, "I believe broken window series
[music] one of the best forms of crime
prevention in a community. Why why is
low-level crime not cracked down on very
hard so that you prevent crime [music]
escalating as we've seen in London?